1. PLoS One. 2018 Dec 6;13(12):e0207459. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0207459. 
eCollection 2018.

The multiple maternal legacy of the Late Iron Age group of Urville-Nacqueville 
(France, Normandy) documents a long-standing genetic contact zone in 
northwestern France.

Fischer CE(1), Lefort A(2), Pemonge MH(1), Couture-Veschambre C(1), Rottier 
S(1), Deguilloux MF(1).

Author information:
(1)De la PrΘhistoire α l'Actuel, Culture, Environnement, Anthropologie-UMR 5199, 
CNRS, UniversitΘ de Bordeaux, AllΘe Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, CS, Pessac Cedex, 
France.
(2)Inrap Grand-Ouest, Boulevard de l'Europe, BourguΘbus, France.

Erratum in
    PLoS One. 2019 Jan 25;14(1):e0211519. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0211519.

The compilation of archaeological and genetic data for ancient European human 
groups has provided persuasive evidence for a complex series of migrations, 
population replacements and admixture until the Bronze Age. If the 
Bronze-to-Iron Age transition has been well documented archaeologically, ancient 
DNA (aDNA) remains rare for the latter period and does not precisely reflect the 
genetic diversity of European Celtic groups. In order to document the evolution 
of European communities, we analysed 45 individuals from the Late Iron Age (La 
TΦne) Urville-Nacqueville necropolis in northwestern France, a region recognized 
as a major cultural contact zone between groups from both sides of the Channel. 
The characterization of 37 HVS-I mitochondrial sequences and 40 haplogroups 
provided the largest maternal gene pool yet recovered for the European Iron Age. 
First, descriptive analyses allowed us to demonstrate the presence of 
substantial amounts of steppe-related mitochondrial ancestry in the community, 
which is consistent with the expansion of Bell Beaker groups bearing an 
important steppe legacy in northwestern Europe at approximately 2500 BC. Second, 
maternal genetic affinities highlighted with Bronze Age groups from Great 
Britain and the Iberian Peninsula regions tends to support the idea that the 
continuous cultural exchanges documented archaeologically across the Channel and 
along the Atlantic coast (during and after the Bronze Age period) were 
accompanied by significant gene flow. Lastly, our results suggest a maternal 
genetic continuity between Bronze Age and Iron Age groups that would argue in 
favour of a cultural transition linked to progressive local economic changes 
rather than to a massive influx of allochthone groups. The palaeogenetic data 
gathered for the Urville-Nacqueville group constitute an important step in the 
biological characterization of European Iron age groups. Clearly, more numerous 
and diachronic aDNA data are needed to fully understand the complex relationship 
between the cultural and biological evolution of groups from the period.

DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0207459
PMCID: PMC6283558
PMID: 30521562 [Indexed for MEDLINE]

Conflict of interest statement: The authors have declared that no competing 
interests exist.
