1. Burns. 2018 Jun;44(4):995-999. doi: 10.1016/j.burns.2017.05.024. Epub 2018 Apr
 12.

Epidemiology of bus fires in mainland China from 2006 to 2015.

Liu Y(1), Wu P(2), Ho JK(3), Hua H(4), Chen H(2), Cen Y(1), Guo S(2), Han C(2), 
Wang X(5).

Author information:
(1)Department of Burn and Plastic Surgery, West China Hospital of Sichuan 
University, Chengdu 610041, China.
(2)Department of Burns & Wound Care Center, Second Affiliated Hospital of 
Zhejiang University College of Medicine, Hangzhou 310009, China.
(3)Department of Burns & Wound Care Center, Second Affiliated Hospital of 
Zhejiang University College of Medicine, Hangzhou 310009, China; College of 
Medicine, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310000, China.
(4)Department of Burns & Wound Care Center, Second Affiliated Hospital of 
Zhejiang University College of Medicine, Hangzhou 310009, China; Department of 
Nursing, Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University College of Medicine, 
Hangzhou, China.
(5)Department of Burns & Wound Care Center, Second Affiliated Hospital of 
Zhejiang University College of Medicine, Hangzhou 310009, China. Electronic 
address: wangxingang8157@zju.edu.cn.

OBJECTIVE: This study analyses the epidemiological characteristics of bus fires 
in mainland China over the past 10 years to develop prevention strategies and 
emergency procedures for such incidence and the resulting casualties.
METHODS: We collected reports on bus fires from the media and news websites and 
looked up on Medline, PubMed, and Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure 
databases for relevant publications in English or Chinese from January 1, 2006 
to December 31, 2015.
RESULTS: In the past 10 years, there were 382 bus fires in mainland China. The 
frequency of fires was markedly higher in 2013 and 2014. The vast majority 
(89.1%) of the fires were caused by spontaneous combustion, followed by arson 
(5.0%). There were reports of casualties in 41 (10.7%) of the bus fires, 
including 144 deaths and 567 injuries. The fires leading to casualties resulted 
from spontaneous combustion in 22 (53.7%) incidents, arson in 12 (29.3%) 
incidents, and traffic accidents in 7 (17.1%) incidents. Arson caused the most 
casualties, including 91 deaths and 323 injuries.
CONCLUSIONS: This epidemiological study presents characteristic findings related 
to bus fires in China mainland. The general trend of bus fires showed a gradual 
increase but with a fluctuation in several years. The regional distribution of 
bus fires revealed some specific characteristics, and most of bus fires happened 
in those regions locating in the eastern area of China mainland. The largest 
number of bus fires were caused by spontaneous combustion. Bus fires caused by 
arson accounting for only 5% of the total bus fires resulted in the most severe 
casualties. Most of bus arson occurred in the morning and evening rush hours.

Copyright ⌐ 2017 Elsevier Ltd and ISBI. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.burns.2017.05.024
PMID: 29657095 [Indexed for MEDLINE]
